בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מז, Mem Zayin, 47,
and we continue in our discussion of the משנה Mishnah of somebody
who is counting off individual dates or whatever, and he says, "Marry
me with this, and with this, and with this, and this, and
this, and this," whether each one is a separate act or it's
one act, you combine the dates to have a שוה פרוטה shaveh
perutah or each individual date, and so forth. Okay, within that context,
we pick up on the bottom of מו עמוד ב, Mem Vav
Amud Bet, and we are, let's see... the גמרא Gemara says, ואיבעית
אימא, V'iba'it eima,
it is about two lines above the תוספות Tosafot שכתב, she'kasav, it
is, I don't even know how, about 20 lines from the bottom,
line starts with word בחמנא. bechamna. And the issue here is the
גמרא Gemara has momentarily moved away from this question about counting off
the dates and asks a different question. If somebody marries a woman
and then it works out for some reason the קידושין kiddushin didn't
take effect, does she have to give the money back? Is the
money a gift or is the money a
פקדון, pikadon, a type of a, how do you translate פקדון? pikadon?
An entrusted object, yeah,
some object to be watched. That's what he says, right?
So,
well, obviously if he says explicitly... the question is how legally do
we interpret if nothing else is said. So the גמרא Gemara frames
the question as a debate of רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel if somebody
marries his sister, where presumably everybody knows that that's not a real
קידושין, kiddushin, does she have to give the money back or can
she keep the money? רב Rav says she has to give it
back, which I think makes the most sense. Why should we read
into this a new transaction of a gift? And שמואל Shmuel says
that she can keep it. So within שמואל, Shmuel, we're asking from
a case of somebody who takes חלה challah but takes it in
the קמח, kemach, in the flour, not before it's dough, and gives
it to the כהן. kohen. It's a similar type of a thing,
a transaction which everybody should have should assume and presumably knows is
no good, and the הלכה halakhah is that the כהן kohen has
to give the flour back. He doesn't get to keep it, so
that seems to support רב's Rav position. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara explains that no, according to שמואל, Shmuel, the reason for that
is if he keeps the flour, he'll think actually it was good
חלה challah and that'll lead to to transgressing various things. So you
give it back as a way of reinforcing that it was not
good חלה. challah. So now the גמרא Gemara within that context sort
of asks the similar question on that same idea. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it
eima, says the גמרא, Gemara, you could also say, לעולם כהן מציית.
le'olam kohen metzayet. If we were to tell the כהן, kohen, why
not, says the גמרא, Gemara, tell the כהן kohen keep the flour
but דמפריש תרומה dimafresh terumah on the flour or חלה challah on
the flour? So that'll let the כהן kohen know that the flour
is not really חלה. challah. So we can let him keep it
and according to שמואל Shmuel we should let him keep it. מציית,
Metzayet, he'll listen to us if we tell him to be מפריש
mafrish the חלה. challah. So even if you say the כהן kohen
would listen to us if we tell him to be מפריש חלה
mafrish challah on the flour, דקסבר בעל הבית מתנה הוא דעבד, dekasvar
ba'al habayit matanah hu d'avad, the problem will be that the owner
who gave the flour is not going to see the כהן kohen
redo it and therefore from the owner's perspective he gave flour and
we're telling him you're done, you're not getting your flour back. So
from his perspective he's done and he was מפריש חלה. mafrish challah.
And now he can eat the dough that he's going to make
from this flour, okay, but which is טבל, tevel, which hasn't had
חלה challah taken. ואתי למיכל בטבל, V'atei lemeichal betevel, he'll eat it
while it's still טבל. tevel. So therefore from the owner's perspective he
has to get the flour back so he understands that it didn't
work. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמרת אדם יודע שאין מפרישין חלה
קמח. Amarta adam yodeia she'ein mafrishin challah kemach. Well one minute, but
you said that everybody knows that חלה challah can't be taken while
it's still flour. יודע ואינו יודע, Yodeia v'eino yodeia, sort of
knows. Okay? יודע שאין מפרישין חלה קמח, Yodeia she'ein mafrishin challah kemach,
he knows you don't do it, you don't normally do it, ואינו
יודע, v'eino yodeia, but what he doesn't know is
דסבר טעמא מאי משום טירחא דכהן. desavar ta'ama mai mishum tircha d'kohen.
It's not really that it doesn't take effect if you do it.
The reason you're not supposed to do it, he doesn't know reasons,
people just know the norm is not to do it, but he
thinks maybe if you do it it works, and maybe the only
reason you don't do it is because it's not fair to the
כהן, kohen, you have to make the כהן kohen work extra to
turn it into dough. וטירחא דכהן קבלה, V'tircha d'kohen kablah, and the
כהן kohen was willing to accept the flour. So he figures בדיעבד
bedi'avad it might work. So he's not 100% sure it doesn't work.
So you have to make sure you give him the flour back
in order that he understands that it didn't work. And but so
fundamentally שמואל Shmuel says I'd let people keep what was given to
them in this type of a context. Here it has to be
given back so there's no confusion of the הלכה. halakhah. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, ותהוי תרומה ויחזור ויתרום? V'tehavi terumah v'yachzor
veyitrom? Well one minute, we can do something else that signals to
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit that it wasn't good חלה. challah. Let
the כהן kohen keep the flour and tell the בעל הבית ba'al
habayit he has to take חלה challah second time. Okay, we use
the phrase תרומה terumah here, well because besides that חלה challah is
called תרומה, terumah, but because that's a concept we have elsewhere that
we can say it was good תרומה terumah and you have to
take תרומה terumah second time because it really wasn't good, but let
the כהן kohen keep the תרומה terumah and you take it a
second time. Is that here? Let the כהן kohen keep it, let
the בעל הבית balabos take חלה challah a second time and that'll
signal to the בעל הבית balabos that it wasn't really good. ומי
לא תנן, U-mi lo tnan, we have something just like that. מי
שאינו נקב על הנקב, Mi she-eino nakev al ha-nakev, if somebody takes
from hydroponic plants and he's מפריש mafrish the hydroponic tomatoes that it
should be good תרומה terumah on the tomatoes that grew in the
soil, okay, which isn't because obviously the hydroponic are not דאורייתא de-Oraita
obligated and the stuff that grew in the soil is, okay, so
in that case what do we say? He says תרומה, terumah, the
כהן kohen gets to keep those tomatoes, ויחזור ויתרום, ve-yachzor ve-yitrom, but
he has to take a second time, obviously from the soil tomatoes
on the soil tomatoes. So anyway, we can let the כהן kohen
keep it and tell you that you have to do it a
second time and that'll signal to you that it wasn't really good.
So why not say that here? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
הא קמיה בתרי מני ציית ובהא מני לא ציית. Ha kamyei be-trei
minei tsayet u-ve-hai mana lo tsayet. No, no, no, we remember we
said earlier yesterday
that to tell somebody the hydroponic tomatoes didn't really work on the
soil tomatoes and you have to do it a second time, that's
תרי מיני, trei minei, two fundamentally separate types of things, they'll believe
us and they'll listen to us and they'll take a second time.
But to tell him the כהן kohen gets to keep the flour
and you have to do it a second time, it's like what's
the difference? I mean, it's all the same
thing. So why should I have to do it a second time?
It's not like he understands that there's a problem there once you're
letting the כהן kohen keep the flour. So therefore that won't work.
Unless the כהן kohen gives back the flour, they're not going to
listen and pay attention and he won't take a second time and
we'll have problems. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולא ציית? ve-lo
tsayet? Is that really true? That somebody won't listen to us to
do it a second time even if it's all fundamentally the same
object? והתנן, Ve-ha-tnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, התורם קישות ונמצאת
מרה, ha-torem kishut ve-nimtset morah,
somebody separated off קישות kishut which I think is a type of
a gourd and then it was bitter, okay, so he took one
gourd out of a hundred but it turns out that the gourd
that he took was actually inedible, it had gone rotten, אבטיח ונמצאת
סרוח, avatiach ve-nimtset saruach, or a watermelon and it was sour, תרומה
ויחזור ויתרום. terumah ve-yachzor ve-yitrom.
So the כהן kohen keeps what was given to him but you
have to take a second time. So there it's all one thing,
it's all gourds, it's all watermelons, okay, but nevertheless we say it
works and take a second time.
No, two things.
What do you mean? From the outside it all looks like watermelon.
Okay. When you opened it up, it was sour.
Okay, so it was a sour one and a good
one.
Okay, it's flour and it's dough. I mean, the point is you
could say that maybe since when you opened that opaque, but fundamentally
people don't think of it as a different category. They think of
it as I took a watermelon. If you tell me it's good,
why should I have to take another watermelon? All right, anyway, that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. So you see if somebody would listen to
us to take another watermelon, he should listen to us to take
תרומה terumah again from the flour once it becomes dough. So the
גמרא Gemara says
no, שאני התם דמדאורייתא תרומה מעליא היא. shani hatam de-mi-de-Oraita terumah ma'alya
hi. No, no, no, there even if he doesn't listen to us,
it's not so bad because biblically speaking if you took from the
same מין, min, even if it was sour or if it had
gone bad, presumably it's still somewhat edible, it's not
inedible, okay, that still works בדיעבד. bedi'avad. So even if he doesn't
listen to us to do a second time, at least he still
was מפריש תרומה דאורייתא. mafrish terumah de-Oraita. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, how do you
know
that? דאמר רבי אילא, De-amar Rabbi Ila, דאמר רבי אילא, de-amar Rabbi
Ila, מנין לתורם מן הרע על היפה שתרומתו תרומה? minayin la-torem min
ha-ra al ha-yafeh she-trumato terumah? How do you know that בדיעבד bedi'avad
you're not supposed to take from the bad grain on the good
grain, but if you did how do you know post facto it
works? שנאמר ולא תשאו עליו חטא בהרימכם את חלבו ממנו, She-ne'emar ve-lo
tise'u alav cheit be-harimechem et chelbo mimenu, you shall not bear the
burden of sin when you take the fat, the good stuff, for
the תרומה, terumah, then you won't be sinning, okay, which means that
if you don't take the good stuff for the תרומה, terumah, you
only take the bad stuff for the תרומה, terumah, you will be
sinning. So now how does that prove that it worked? Because he
says אם אינו קדוש נשיאת חטא למה? im eino kadosh nesi'at cheit
lamah? But if it didn't work בדיעבד, bedi'avad, why are you bearing
the burden of the sin? Right? If you tried to take the
bad on the good and it didn't work, why would you have
sinned? You didn't do anything yet, maybe you tried to do something
wrong but it didn't have an effect. So the פסוק pasuk implies
that you have done a sin when you take from the bad
on the good, that means that it actually will have been effective
and the תרומה terumah will be חל chal but it will be
a sinful תרומה terumah because it will be the bad on the
good. Okay.
Why is it saying the opposite, that you not bear sin if
you do what's right? That's kind of weird.
I understand but that's
since, in other words, the חטא, cheit, it can only be a
חטא cheit if the מעשה ma'aseh you did was חל. chal.
Right. But then תוספות Tosafot actually asks the question about that because
you're generalizing correctly
which is, but תוספות Tosafot points out I mean there's a whole
discussion in תמורה Temurah which is כל מילתא דאמר רחמנא לא תעביד
אי עביד מהני או לא מהני. kol milta de-amar Rachmana la ta'avid
i avid mahani o lo mahani.
If the תורה Torah says don't do X and you went ahead
and did it, does it take effect or not? Okay. Which obviously
there are some real-world things that take effect like don't murder, you
murdered someone, he's dead. Okay. But other types of things might not
take effect like if you're not supposed, I know there when it
says לא יוכל לשלחה כל ימיו lo yuchal leshalcha kol yamav by
the case of the אונס, ones, right? The guy who rapes this
woman, let's say he gave her a גט, get, is the גט
get חל? chal? maybe we won't legally recognize the effect of that.
Right, you're not supposed, כהנים kohanim aren't supposed to marry certain women,
right, but we know that that is חל. chal. עריות, arayos, no,
the איסורי ערווה issurei erva are חל, chal, but the איסורי לאו
issurei lav aren't חל. chal. So some types of things you know
now, but if it חל chal as soon as he gives her
the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, if it didn't take effect or maybe
only after they've had sex. So when you actually do something to
the point that you've transgressed, do we assume that that would act,
you know, that the thing actually takes effect or not? So that's
the whole discussion in תמורה, Temurah, fascinating discussion. Here the גמרא Gemara
assumes that you would not have sinned if it did not have
some, if it did not take effect. תוספות Tosafot ask, but how
does that fit in because we have actually opinions that say otherwise
as a general rule? So he tries to explain why the גמרא
Gemara is מדייק medayek specifically from this פסוק. pasuk. Even if the
general rule is you can be punished for something that didn't take
effect, just because you did against what the Torah said you're supposed
to do, even if it didn't, wasn't legally effective, effectuated, nevertheless here
the גמרא Gemara understands that it's only when if it takes, if
it's only if it takes effect. Okay, so it's a good point
to generalize it, but there's a, but actually the more general question
is debated. In this specific case, we're saying that you would only
have transgressed if it actually was good תרומה. terumah. Okay? מכאן לתורם
מן הרע על היפה, mikan latorum min hara al hayaffe, so because
it says that you will have bear a sin and you will
and you if you don't take from the good, from here you
see that if you take from the bad on the good, שתרומתו
תרומה shetrumasu terumah that it does take effect. Okay. So basically we've
explained that according to שמואל, Shmuel, if you
gave, if somebody married his sister, she gets to keep the ring.
Okay? And the reason that the כהן kohen doesn't keep the flower,
in this case of חלה, challah, is because if he doesn't, either
the כהן kohen will get confused and think it's good, or the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis will get confused and think it was good,
and the other solutions like have them separate a second time or
whatever won't work, they won't listen to us and it won't, you
know, won't have the same effect as saying give back the flower.
And the reason you can tell them elsewhere take a second time
is either because it was two separate things, the hydroponic and the
soil, and they believe us when we say a second time, or
even if it was one thing like the watermelon, then one of
them was sour, if they don't believe it, it's not the worst
thing because in the end it really was good תרומה. terumah. Okay.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Now that is the end, it's too bad
we got a little behind because that was like the perfect end
of yesterday's דף daf because that was the entire end of that
סוגיא sugya about somebody who marries his sister, okay, and what happens
with the money, it's a more general question, right, in the end
the קידושין kiddushin didn't work, do you give back the money or
does she keep the money? As I said nowadays not exactly the
same, but you know there's all these questions about somebody
gives a woman an engagement ring and then the engagement gets called
off, right? So is it a מתנה matanah or is it, was
it only a מתנה matanah on the understanding that they were eventually
going to get married? I don't know, I mean I wonder if
that's actually come to the court. I imagine that she's supposed to
give it back. I imagine it's all implicitly בתנאי, betnai, I don't
know, I don't know. Anyway, so that was the debate of רב
Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but now we turn back to our משנה.
Mishnah. And our משנה Mishnah was with counting out the dates
and if you say marry me with this, marry me with this,
each one is separate act, but if you say with this, with
this, with this, with this, it's all one big act and it
all has to be worth a פרוטה perutah and it's okay if
it's all worth a פרוטה perutah together. Okay. So אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, top of מ"ז ע"א. mem zayin amud aleph.
So now we're switching back to the topic of our משנה. Mishnah.
לא שנו אלא דאמר לה בזו ובזו ובזו. lo shanu ela de’amar
la bezu uvezu uvezu. When is it that they're considered to be,
now we're, he's also going back to the issue of remember when
she eats the individual dates before, you know, he's saying this, this,
this, and each date that he puts down, she's putting in her
mouth and she's eating, right, this case. So she's eating, eating, eating,
eating, eating, and when he finally says the last ובזו, uvezu, the
act of קידושין kiddushin is done. So this stuff is considered what
we explained a מלווה milveh
because
it's not around when the act of קידושין kiddushin is done, it's
just stuff that gets back to our issue that she'd have to
pay it back, the type of thing we were talking about until
now, right, she's already eaten it. So that's a מלווה, milveh, he
can't marry her with this, he can only marry her with the
last one which is still around when he finishes his statement, and
that last one has to be worth a פרוטה. perutah.
It doesn't matter, right, she gobbles, no, it can't be, it has
to be some time in between because they're not pitted.
Okay. לא שנו אלא דאמר לה בזו ובזו ובזו. lo shanu ela
de’amar la bezu uvezu uvezu. When is it that if she eats
it before, you know, then it becomes a מלווה milveh and those
dates don't count towards the שווה פרוטה? shaveh perutah? That's only if
he says this, and this, and this. אבל אמר לה באלו, aval
amar la be'elu, okay, like he's got a group of dates in
his hands, and he says marry me with these, all the dates
I'm having in my hands. And then he starts handing them to
her, one and the next, and each one he hands to her
she eats. Okay. So then he says אפילו אוכלת נמי מקודשת, afillu
ocheles nami mekudeshes, even if she's eating them as he's giving them
to her singly, she's married. Why? כי קאכלה מדידה קאכלה, ki ka'achla
midida ka'achla, because it's all hers. Okay, meaning in this case the
problem was was that the statement that defined that the, like the
act of קידושין kiddushin was done at the end, and then only
when the act of, the words of קידושין kiddushin that defined it
were finished. he only gave her one thing. But here the entire
statement is done, marry me with these. The entire statement is done.
So everything she takes is now giving her her כסף קידושין. kesef
kiddushin. It's already been designated as everything in my hand is her
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. So now she's entitled to do whatever she
wants with it, right? It's not a מלוה. milveh. The words that
define the act of קידושין kiddushin are done and now everything that's
being given, I'm just taking my time giving it to her, but
it's all her own thing.
What's interesting here to me is that in this scenario, her eating
them is like a גילוי דעת giluy da'at that she's accepted the...
No, that's true. I mean, she first takes it before she eats
it. So she doesn't need that גילוי דעת. giluy da'at. I guess
if he threw it in the air and she caught it in
her mouth... but I mean the eating, you don't need the גילוי
דעת giluy da'at of the eating. The גילוי דעת giluy da'at is
first she accepts it. Right. Right. But the point is that then
all the dates combined can be worth a פרוטה prutah because the
problem here was the reason you couldn't use those earlier dates was
because you were still in the middle of the act and therefore
it was not yet
determined, it wasn't already labeled as these are dates of קידושין. kiddushin.
These might have been dates of a מלוה milveh because it wasn't
clear, the act wasn't done, finished yet. It's only finished here. Whereas
here when he says marry me with these and she starts accepting
it, it's clear that she's agreed to the קידושין kiddushin and this
is the receiving of the money of the קידושין kiddushin and therefore
that already clearly labels all of these dates as the כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. So it all combines. There's no reason she should have
to leave it all and not eat it once she takes it
and it's hers and it's hers under the context of כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin. She can do what she wants with it.
Yes. So it doesn't matter whether she's eating the dates or not?
Because when she's eating them and it's given to her singly, בזו
ובזו ובזו ובזו, bezo vezo vezo vezo, then they can't count towards
the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
That's what I mean. What if he just gave her one?
Then of course it works. Of course it works. The חידוש chiddush
is that even if she eats it and it's not around by
the time he gives her the last one and only when they're
all combined are they worth a פרוטה, prutah, each one is only
worth a fifth of a פרוטה prutah and he's giving her five.
So you might think well since by the time he gives her
the fifth and only then has he fully given her a פרוטה,
prutah, the other four-fifths of the פרוטה prutah are not around anymore,
maybe it doesn't work. Right? So the point is it does work
because he clearly designated all of them as the money before he
started giving it to her.
I'm assuming you're asking about if she didn't eat the dates in
either case, the case where he said it once...
If she didn't eat the dates, it works in both cases. Right.
But but if he did she did start eating the dates, then
in this case בזו בזו בזו bezo bezo bezo it doesn't work,
right? Unless the last one is worth a פרוטה. prutah. But you
can't use these for the פרוטה.
prutah. Plus who keeps dates for, can you
imagine a date not being worth a פרוטה prutah now? Or it
would be...
imagine it's raisins, okay? אבל אמר לה... Aval amar lah...
imagine it's raisins, okay? אבל Aval okay fine. תני כוותיה דרבא. Tanni
kivateih deRava. We taught like רבא. Rava. התקדשי לי באלון ברימון ובאגוז.
hikadsheli be'alon berimon uve'egoz.
Marry me with... I don't know what an אלון alon is.
An אלון alon now is considered a pine tree. But אלון... alon...
an acorn? Okay. Oak tree.
אלון alon is
an oak tree. An acorn, a pomegranate, or a nut. או שאמר
לה... O she'amar lah... or he said to her, התקדשי לי באלו,
hikadsheli be'eilu, all of these. Okay? So presumably the first case is
he said he named the fruit in his hand: marry me with
this apple, pear and orange. Or he just said the word אלו,
eilu, but presumably he finished his statement before he started giving it
to her. Okay. אם יש בכולן שוה פרוטה מקודשת ואם לאו אינה
מקודשת. Im yesh bekulan shaveh prutah mekudeshet ve'im lav einah mekudeshet. So
as a group it's sufficient that they have a פרוטה, prutah, they
don't have to be worth a פרוטה prutah individually. בזו ובזו ובזו.
bezo vezo vezo. Now similarly, because the first case is she didn't
start eating. The first case is he gave it to her before
she did anything. So similarly if he just said this, this and
this, אם יש בכולן שוה פרוטה מקודשת ואם לאו אינה מקודשת, im
yesh bekulan shaveh prutah mekudeshet ve'im lav einah mekudeshet, same הלכה. halacha.
If it's all worth a פרוטה prutah it works, if not it
doesn't work. You can count them all because this was a case
where she didn't eat them and he so so by the time
he was done she had a פרוטה prutah sitting in front of
her. Now בזו, bezo, it is this, נטלתה ואכלתו, netatava ve'achaltu, and
she took it and ate it. בזו, bezo, and this one, נטלתה
ואכלתו, netatava ve'achaltu, and she take it and ate it. ועוד בזו,
ve'od bezo, and also this, ועוד בזו, ve'od bezo, אינה מקודשת. einah
mekudeshet. If she was eating each one individually it doesn't work, עד
שבאחת מהן שוה פרוטה, ad shebe'achat mehen shaveh prutah, unless there is
one of them, which we said later meant the last one, by
the time he's done with his statement that has to be worth
a פרוטה. prutah. Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: That's
the end of the ברייתא. baraisa. האי באלון ברימון ובאגוז... Hai be'alon
berimon uve'egoz... this acorn, pomegranate and nut. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's
the case? אי דאמר לה או באלון או ברימון או באגוז... iy
de'amar lah o be'alon o berimon o be'egoz... either with this or
with this or with this... אם יש בכולן שוה פרוטה מקודשת? im
yesh bekulan shaveh prutah mekudeshet? How could you say it's enough that
they collectively are worth a פרוטה? prutah? ואו קאמר... ve'o ka'amar... he
said one or the other, not as a collective. ואלא? ve'ella? It
must be that what he's saying is באלון וברימון ובאגוז... be'alon uverimon
uve'egoz... all three of them together. היינו בזו בזו בזו. Hainu bezo
bezo bezo. That's just like the בזו בזו בזו bezo bezo bezo
statement. He didn't use a collective word, באלו. be'eilu. He used a
word that labeled them individually. So why are we having this as
a middle case?
Right. Well, right. In a way, why is it here?
Right. אלא לאו דאמר לה ela lav de'amar lah באלו. ba'elu.
It must be, it must be when he says these three, what
he means is these three like all of them together. It's a
word that's a collective word. והתניא סיפא או שאמר לה התקדשי לי
באלו, ve'hatanya seifa o she'amar lah hitkadshi li ba'elu, but that's the
case that comes right afterwards with these. מכלל דרישא לאו באלו עסקינן.
miklal de'reisha lav ba'elu askinan. So it sounds like the pomegranate and
the nut case is not a
באלו ba'elu case. פירושא קמפרש. perusha kampharesh. It's really just
explaining. התקדשי לי באלון ברימון ובאגוז hitkadshi li be'alon be'rimon u've'egoz כיצד,
keitzad, how would that work? כגון דאמר לה התקדשי לי באלו. kegon
de'amar lah hitkadshi li ba'elu. If he said באלו. ba'elu. So basically
the first thing we did is we sort of neutralized the אלון
דרימון alon de'rimon case and said it was an example of
באלו. ba'elu. Now what's more interesting to us is that the ברייתא
braita really repeats itself, right? That it says, it says:
If
he says באלו ba'elu and it says כולם שווה פרוטה מקודשת, kulam
shaveh prutah mekudeshet, then it says בזו ובזו ובזו bezo u'vezo u'vezo
and it has the same הלכה, halacha, all of them together have
to have a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. That's what the ברייתא braita
said. It had the אלון alon and the רימון rimon but we
made it into a באלו ba'elu case. And then after בזו ובזו
ובזו, bezo u'vezo u'vezo, it says if it was אוכלת ochelet and
he said בזו ועוד בזו bezo ve'od bezo etc., then you need
to have the last one. It says one of them, but we
say it means the last one has to be a שווה פרוטה.
shaveh prutah. It's not enough that all as a collective. Okay, so
what the גמרא gemara is going to say is, it sounds like
the idea that the אוכלת ochelet makes a difference so it's not
enough that they have it as a group, but only one of
them, each one individual has to be a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah.
It sounds like אוכלת ochelet only makes a difference in the בזו
bezo case. Because we had a case of אלון ורימון alon u'rimon
which we basically made into a באלו ba'elu case. Okay, then we
had a בזו bezo case and then we talked about eating in
the בזו bezo case. It sounds like the eating wouldn't make a
difference in the באלו ba'elu case and that's a support to רבא.
Rava. Okay, so it says like this. So it says כגון דאמר
לה התקדשי לי באלו.
kegon de'amar lah hitkadshi
li ba'elu. ותני סיפא בזו נטלה ואכלתו, אם יש באחת מהן שווה
פרוטה מקודשת, ואם לאו אינה מקודשת. ve'tani seifa bezo natla ve'achalto, im
yesh be'achat mehen shaveh prutah mekudeshet, ve'im lav einah mekudeshet. ואילו רישא
לא קמפלג בין אוכלת למנחת. ve'ilu reisha lo kamphalig bein ochelet le'manachat.
It doesn't
distinguish between whether she leaves the stuff in front of her or
she eats it. Eating was only presented as a problem in the
second scenario, בזו בזו בזו. bezo bezo bezo.
So the גמרא gemara says אלמא שמע מינה, כל היכא דאמר לה
באלו, alma shema mina, kol heicha de'amar lah ba'elu,
as long as he said באלו ba'elu at the outset, כי קאכלה
מדידה קאכלה, ki ka'achla mideida ka'achla,
when she's eating, she's eating what's already hers. So it's not a
problem like the status of this has not yet been identified and
therefore when it's clarified at that stage, it's a מילתא. milta. No,
it's clarified at the beginning. It's כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, everything combined
is a פרוטה. prutah. Now you're just eating the money that's being
given to you as כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin and it works. שמע
מינה. shema mina. Oh, that's good. So that was a very nice
ברייתא braita that supported רבא Rava's statement. Now the גמרא gemara says
like this. One minute. All of this works very nicely. If you
remember back to yesterday, this issue of eating, okay, that was explained
by who was it? We've been working
with the explanation of not רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel but רבי אמי.
Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said that this idea of eating
is going on the case of בזו ובזו
ובזו. bezo u'vezo u'vezo. But רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel said the case
of eating was going on the case where he said התקדשי לי
בזו, התקדשי לי בזו, התקדשי לי בזו hitkadshi li bezo, hitkadshi li
bezo, hitkadshi li bezo and she ate it. But then the problem
was that there was no חידוש chiddush to that. Of course that
works if any one of them has a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah.
You remember this from yesterday? Everybody remember this? I'll remind you. Okay?
The
משנה mishna said like this. The משנה mishna said if he said
התקדשי לי בזו,
hitkadshi li
bezo, התקדשי לי hitkadshi li and then התקדשי לי hitkadshi li etc.
התקדשי לי. hitkadshi li. So in that case you need one has
to be a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. If you said בזו ובזו
ובזו, bezo u'vezo u'vezo,
then
the group
has to be a שווה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, not
one, okay? Because you're making them all part of the group. And
then it says if it was אוכלת, ochelet, then one has to
be a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. So the question is which case
was this going on, the אוכלת? ochelet? Okay, so רב אמי Rav
Ami said אוכלת ochelet was going on the בזו ובזו bezo u'vezo
which is what we just explained here. That was clear. You know,
it says בזו ואכלתו, ועוד בזו ואכלתו, ועוד בזו ואכלתו. bezo ve'achalto,
ve'od bezo ve'achalto, ve'od bezo ve'achalto.
That's clear that that's what was going on in the ברייתא. braita.
That's what we've been working on. That's what רב אמי Rav Ami
said. That if she's eating it, so then you're left with just
the last one to work, and the last one has to be
a שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. Okay, so that's what we've been working
with. But רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel said no, no, no, אוכלת ochelet
was going up here when Each one was a separate act. So
the question is, but that's what we've already said, that when each
one is a separate act, each one has to be a, or
one of them separately by itself has to be a שווה פרוטה.
shaveh perutah. How does it make it any different? And then it
doesn't make it any different. It's just a חידוש chidush that even
though she's eating it, it still has to be a שווה פרוטה.
shaveh perutah. Do people remember that from yesterday? Okay. So the problem
is we have a ברייתא braita that clearly is following רב אמי.
Rav Ami. It says: בזו be-zo and to eat it, בזו be-zo
and to eat it, בזו be-zo and to eat it. It was
the בזו בזו be-zo be-zo case. But רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel said
the אכלת ochlat was the case of התקדשי לי. hitkadshi li. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. It says, the
גמרא Gemara says like this: הניחא למאן דאמר אסיפא
קאי. hani kha le-man de-amar aseifa
kai. This ברייתא braita works very well according to רב אמי Rav
Ami that says the אכלת ochlat scenario was going on the end
of the משנה, mishna, the בזו בזו בזו. be-zo be-zo be-zo. And
that's clearly what we're, what this ברייתא's braita talking about. ומאי עד
שתהא באחת מהן שווה פרוטה? u-mai ad she-tei be-achat me-hen shaveh perutah?
And he said, what does it mean one has to have a
שווה פרוטה? shaveh perutah? It means
עד שתהא באחרונה שווה פרוטה, ad she-tei be-achronah shaveh perutah, the last
one. Because until then the act of קידושין kiddushin isn't done. And
when the act of קידושין kiddushin is done, the only one that's
left around is the last one, so the last one has to
have a שווה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. הכא נמי, hakha nami, עד שתהא
באחרונה שווה פרוטה, ad she-tei be-achronah shaveh perutah, he'd explain this ברייתא
braita the same way. But it's clear that the basic case of
the ברייתא braita is the case of בזו be-zo and eating, בזו
be-zo and eating etc., not a case of הרי את מקודשת, harei
at mekudeshet, הרי את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, separate acts. אלא רב
ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, ella Rav u-Shmuel de-amri tufaya, but according to רב
ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel that both say, ארישא קאי, areisha kai, that the
אכלת ochlat was going on the first case of the משנה, mishna,
ואכלת איצטריכא ליה, ve-ochlat itztrikhlei, and there was a חידוש, chidush, even
if she eats and she's getting immediate הנאה, hana'ah, it still has
to be worth a שווה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. But basically it was
going on a case of הרי את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, הרי
את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, separate acts. Not a בזו בזו בזו
be-zo be-zo be-zo case. So according to them, so הכא כללי קחשיב
פרטי לא קחשיב. hakha klali kakhashiv prati lo kakhashiv. In our case,
the בזו בזו בזו be-zo be-zo be-zo is case of what's called
כללי, klali, כללי klali means that they're working as a group. It's
one big type of act of קידושין, kiddushin, not פרטי. prati. פרטי
prati is each thing is a separate act, התקדשי לי בזו, hitkadshi
li be-zo, התקדשי לי בזו. hitkadshi li be-zo. You understand how that's
a פרט prat and the other's a כלל, klal, where כללים klals
are working as a group. So our ברייתא braita makes it clear
that the eating is in a scenario of them as a group,
and רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel said the eating was only working in
a scenario where each statement was a separate statement, פרטי. prati. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. הא מני רבי היא. ha-mani Rebbi hi.
No, our ברייתא braita could be רבי, Rebbi, דאמר לא שנא כזית
כזית ולא שנא כזית וכזית תרתי הויין. de-amar lo shena ke-zayit ke-zayit
ve-lo shena ke-zayit u-k-zayit trata ha-vei. רבי Rebbi says, remember we said
at the beginning of the משנה mishna that that was following רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, who said that the only way you separate the
statement is by saying like שבועה לזה, shvuah la-zeh, you know, שבועה
לזה, shvuah la-zeh, שבועה לזה, shvuah la-zeh, שבועה לזה. shvuah la-zeh. הרי
את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, הרי את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, הרי
את מקודשת. harei at mekudeshet. You need to make fully separate statements
in order to separate the acts. But there are other opinions out
there. That according to one opinion if you say שבועה לא לך
ולא לך ולא לך, shvuah lo le-kha ve-lo le-kha ve-lo le-kha, that's
actually separate שבועות. shvuahs. So the same way that there's a debate
by that, is also similar discussion about with which is this case
about somebody a כהן kohen that has a thought of פיגול. pigul.
Like these are some of the סוגיות sugyas you never get away
from in ש"ס: shas: יבמות, yevamot, ייבום, yibum, פיגול, pigul, the עציץ
שאינו נקוב. atzitz she-eino nakuv. Anyway, so if a כהן kohen is
having a thought about פיגול pigul and says I want to eat
a כזית ke-zayit of this קרבן korban at this time and a
כזית ke-zayit at that time or whatever, are they separate acts of
פיגול pigul or one act of פיגול? pigul? Similar question. And רבי
Rebbi says that even if you say I'm going to eat a
כזית ke-zayit here and a כזית ke-zayit here and a כזית ke-zayit
here those are separate acts of פיגול. pigul. Okay. And it doesn't
matter if you say כזית כזית ke-zayit ke-zayit or you say כזית
וכזית. ke-zayit u-k-zayit. Whether you even have the word and or not.
Okay. Each one makes it a separate act of פיגול. pigul. Similarly
here, okay, the בזו בזו בזו בזו, be-zo be-zo be-zo be-zo, even
though you interestingly say
ובזו, ve-o-ve-zo, ובזו, ve-o-ve-zo, which certainly sounds like you're turning it into
one big act, the גמרא Gemara says no, the author of this
ברייתא braita would follow רבי Rebbi and actually say that in this
case each one would be a separate act of קידושין. kiddushin. Okay.
So the idea of אכלת ochlat where it says one of them
has to have a שווה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, what we are saying
that means is, you know why one has to have a שווה
פרוטה? shaveh perutah? Because each one is a separate act of קידושין.
kiddushin. And therefore, as long as any one of them has a
שווה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, it works. You can't look at them as
a collective.
Not the
last one.
Not only the last one. Any one according to the way we're
reading. It's just like the התקדשי לי בזו, hitkadshi li be-zo, okay?
All right.
Anyway, this is better in a group just to apply, right? No.
According to the way he ate one at a time?
Yes. The last case is that she's eating one at a time.
Think about that was alone, right? If it was one at a
time.
Yes, but that was because we were following the idea that your
statement wasn't finished until the end. But now we're interpreting the ברייתא
braita according to רבי Rebbi and saying that each one is a
separate act of קידושין. kiddushin. So every one she accepted is a
separate act and if any one of them had a שווה פרוטה
shaveh perutah it works. Yeah.
It reflects my earlier question about like, you know, about the, makes
sense between what he said, it's just, can you ask him later
what he meant? Like afterwards or do we say no like, you
know, you said...
No, no, all of these seem to be legally we have, sort
of like a דברים שבלב אינם דברים Devarim She-balev Ainam Devarim thing,
we have to give a standard interpretation to how to parse these
things.
You can't even ask him afterwards what he meant?
No. Right, I mean presumably there might be some statements where it
was obvious based on context, but then it's not just him reporting
it, there might be other times but yes, I mean it couldn't
make a difference. Okay. Anyway, let's take now, thankfully that's, I mean,
we got the basic idea about that but was a little confusing
all those things about the date or whatever. Now we're able to,
now we're going to go focus directly on the underlying discussion in
principle that can you marry a woman with a debt? Okay, she
owes you a hundred dollars, you're the man, and you say keep
the hundred dollars, you're married to me. So you didn't actually give
her something new.
Now you could say this is the very beginning of המקדש במלוה.
Ha-mekadesh Be-milveh. Now yeah, correct. Now you could say with the benefit
that you will receive by the fact that I will annul your
debt, that's got that's obviously worth some money. You owe me a
hundred dollars. How much would a person pay to be freed from
the obligation to pay the hundred dollars? I mean you could say
it's a hundred dollars, but you know it's not true because you
know people figure I'll pay
later, I'll I can maybe get out of it or whatever. You
know but it's like now sometimes these credit card companies will allow
you right consolidate your debt and you pay a less amount or
something. Anyway, you're obviously could pay some money, you'd pay close to
a hundred, maybe pay fifty, whatever you'd pay so that you wouldn't
have so that to waive the debt. Okay, so if he says
with the cost and the benefit that the wave of the value
of the waiving of the debt, marry me, that would work. Then
he's given her something, it doesn't have to be a physical object.
You might remember for example that the גמרא Gemara had a case
where actually she gave him something, but actually there was a financial
value in him receiving a gift from her. That was dealing in
a sort of scenario of patronage and if somebody is willing to
receive a gift that actually then has some that puts them in
some responsibility towards you and there's actually some you know dollar value
in the fact that somebody agreed to receive a gift from you.
So it doesn't you don't have to receive something concrete. You can
receive some service of value and that acts for קידושין. Kiddushin. So
if he said with the value of waiving the debt, marry me,
and she said yes, it would work. But he didn't say that.
He didn't say the dollar value assigned to the מחילה Mechila of
the חוב. Chov. He said the money you owe me is now
given to you and with that money marry me. But that money,
right, doesn't it's already hers, right. She owes money, what did he
give her? He didn't give her the act of waiving, he gave
her the money but that wasn't exactly his money to give, it
was her money. It was you know so therefore that's the issue
about מקדש במלוה. Me-kadesh Be-milveh. Let's take a look. אמר רב המקדש
במלוה אינה מקודשת מלוה להוצאה ניתנה. Amar Rav Ha-mekadesh Be-milveh Einah Mekudeshet
Milveh Le-hotzaah Nitnah. Now this idea that מלוה להוצאה ניתנה Milveh Le-hotzaah
Nitnah means okay as soon as the money leaves my hand I
would've had my wallet out of here, could've done a better thing,
but let's imagine this is a hundred dollar bill. That's actually not
good, it's confusing because the whole thing is the difference between money,
actually get my wallet. Okay, the whole thing is different. We'll do
a little comparison and contrast.
I already stole his money. Okay.
The whole thing is different between money and right between money and
between other things. So Michael says right here, Michael says lend me
twenty bucks. Okay, and I give him the twenty bucks. Take the
twenty bucks. Okay, I can, can I say wait Michael, that's my
twenty bucks, give it back to me? No.
Sorry, I'm used to this. No.
No, he already has taken pos- it's already even though it's right
there, it's mine, you're holding onto my twenty bucks. No, that dollar
is no longer, that dollar bill is no longer mine. He owes
me twenty dollars. That dollar bill is a hundred percent his. Yes,
hundred percent. I didn't give it to you
as a מתנה. Matanah. That means מלוה להוצאה ניתנה. Milveh Le-hotzaah Nitnah.
So even if let's say Michael here is Michelle, okay so Michelle,
here you are, you know, borrowing twenty bucks and I say you
know what while it's still in your hand, that twenty dollars is
still there, I know I just lent it to you but it's
still in your hand, that was my dollar bill, you're מקודשת Mekudeshet
to me with that. So no, it's no longer my dollar bill.
It's now his. I'm not giving him anything. Okay so that's the
idea of מלוה להוצאה ניתנה. Milveh Le-hotzaah Nitnah. The same way I
can't demand it back, I've already lent him the money. Okay, even
if he still she is still holding onto it, right, she hasn't
even put it in her pocket yet, she's still holding onto it,
I can't say you know what since it's my twenty dollars anyway,
just keep it and it'll be כסף קידושין. Kesef Kiddushin.
So the language of מלוה Milveh refers to the the actual currency
that you've given to the debtor as opposed to forgiving the loan.
Right, that's exactly what I'm saying. If forgiving the loan worked, the
way I'd say that, yeah, הרי את מקודשת לי בהנאת מחילת מלוה.
Harei At Mekudeshet Li Be-hanaat Mechilat Milveh. Okay, that works. But I'm
not doing that. I'm trying to give her the actual money. And
the חידוש Chiddush is is that the money even if it's still
בעין, Be-ayin, it's in her hands, it's fine, it's no longer mine.
Now if I actually said you want Michael you want to borrow
you guess you're Michelle, borrow my cell phone and I give it
to you and now take say you know what just keep the
cell phone and הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li with
that cell phone, that works, because even after he's taken it, it's
still mine, right? He's borrowed it. I can demand it back during
the period of the of the loan, okay, but it's still mine
and I could give it to him, okay, but whereas, whereas with
the money, as soon as it goes into her hands, that dollar
bill is no longer mine.
Do you make a distinction between currency...
I am exactly making a distinction between currency and any other object.
You're both leaning onto it then.
Alright, fine, that's different. Okay, so that's the חידוש. chiddush. If I
said, marry me with the value of waiving the loan, that works.
If I said, marry me with that object I just lent you,
that works, it's my object. But if I lent her 20 bucks
and it's still in her hands and hasn't been spent, it's no
longer my money and I can't ask for the 20 dollars back
and I can't give her the 20 dollars, that's no longer mine
to give. Okay, there's no longer any thing of mine that's in
her possession, there's just a debt. Yes.
But if you gave it to her and then you said with
the value of that loan, marry me?
Right, that works. Yes, I said, yes, I started with that. Yes,
you can always marry if you just reframe it as with the
value
the of me waiving the loan, okay,
but this doesn't work.
Marry me with the money that money you owe me, that loan,
keep the loan and you'll be married to me with it. Okay,
that doesn't work. Okay, מלווה להוצאה ניתנה. milveh l'hotza'ah nitnah. So גמרא
Gemara says, נימא כתנאי, neima kitna'ei, let's say this is like a
debate of תנאים. tanna'im. המקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת ויש אומרים מקודשת. ha-mekadesh
be-milveh einah mekudeshet ve-yesh omrim mekudeshet.
Okay, that certainly sounds like a debate of תנאים tanna'im exactly about
רב'ס Rav's point. Okay, you mean, what do you mean נימא כתנאי,
neima kitna'ei, that's exactly what they're debating. So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי?
mai lav be-ha kamifligi? דמר סבר מלווה להוצאה ניתנה ומר סבר מלווה
לאו להוצאה ניתנה. de-mar savar milveh l'hotza'ah nitnah u-mar savar milveh lav
l'hotza'ah nitnah.
One must assume it's so funny because who really cares what the
reason is, it sounds like they're debating the פסק psak of רב
Rav anyway, right, that one says it works when מקדש במלווה, mekadesh
be-milveh, one says it doesn't. But the גמרא Gemara says presumably they're
debating exactly this question, whether you can marry with the money before
the money's been spent. Okay, one says it's still, it's already no
longer owned by the original owner, and the other says no, it
still is owned by him, let's say that's how we frame it.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ותסברא, ve-tisbera, does that make sense
that that's what's being debated? אימא סיפא, eima seifa, look at the
end of
it, ושוין במכר, ve-shavin be-mecher, let's say because the other thing actually
that works with כסף kessef is not קידושין kiddushin but remember like
buying land. So let's say it was a case of land, שזה
קנה, she-zeh kanah, that it works. So if Michael owes me a
hundred dollars and I say keep the hundred dollars and let me
buy that little plot of land of yours, they agree that it
works. So why would that be different by land than by קידושי
אישה? kiddushei ishah? Now of course you could suggest, we've already seen
ways in which קידושין kiddushin and כסף קידושין kessef kiddushin doesn't follow
the exact parameters as כסף kessef by other קניינים. kinyanim. So maybe
there are some differences here. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. The גמרא Gemara says like this, אי אמרת מלווה לאו להוצאה
ניתנה, ei amrat milveh lav l'hotza'ah nitnah, if everybody if the debate
is that, you know, the issue is that once the money switched
is given for the loan, it no longer is owned by the
owner, it's like it's already spent, so במאי קני? be-mai kani? How
could how could the other side say that it works by land?
There's no money to be given, so it wouldn't make there would
be no logic why it would work wouldn't work by קידושין kiddushin
and would work by land. Okay, so אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav
Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, so that's interesting that the
גמרא Gemara at the outset assumes that this statement that it's making
that מלווה milveh doesn't function as כסף kessef is true both about
קידושין kiddushin and about other things, במכירה, be-mechira, by קרקע. karka. So
therefore you can't explain the difference if it's a simple case. It
must be a more nuanced case. So אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav
Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, הונא חברין, Huna chavrin, הונא
ארכא, Huna archa, הונא Huna our colleague, הונא Huna our long colleague,
מוקים לה במילי אחרי. mokeim lah be-milei acharei.
He says it's talking about a a different type of a
scenario. הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking
about? כגון דאמר לה התקדשי לי במנה ונמצא מנה חסר. kegon de-amar
lah hitkadshi li be-maneh ve-nimtza maneh chaser. So it's not a normal
case of a מלווה. milveh. I lent this woman a hundred dollars
and now I'm saying marry me with the hundred dollars that I've
already given you. No, what happened is, I said to this woman,
marry me with this hundred dollars and she took the hundred dollars
and she counted it out and I was missing a five. It
was only 95 dollars. Okay, so fine, I owe you the other
five. Alright, that's the case. Now, can she be can I marry
her? I said a hundred, but I gave her 95, so the
extra five is like a מלווה. milveh. I'm like I owe that
to you. Will that count towards the hundred as the כסף קידושין?
kessef kiddushin? That's the question.
The מלווה milveh
is in the other direction. The מלווה milveh is the other direct
right, I owe her the money, exactly. Okay, מר סבר כסיפא לה
מילתא למיתבעיה. mar savar kesifa lah milta le-mitva'ei. Is it just 'ashamed'
just those five or the whole?
No, the whole thing, but of those whole thing, the five is
an outstanding loan. Does that still work as if I gave her
the hundred dollars? Okay, so מר סבר כסיפא לה מילתא למיתבעיה, mar
savar kesifa lah milta le-mitva'ei, she's embarrassed to ask for the other
five. I gave her 95 dollars, she's now my wife or whatever,
she's not gonna ask for it, and therefore even if she says
okay and she even if she... she says okay and she agrees
to it, it’s not like she really was okay and she really
felt that she received the hundred dollars because deep down she’s feeling
like I’m never gonna get those five dollars. And I said I
was gonna give her a hundred dollars. So therefore it wouldn’t work.
ומר סבר לא כסיפא לה מילתא למיתבע. Umar savar lo kesifa lah
milta lemitba. No, she’s not embarrassed to ask for it.
That’s a מחלוקת תנאים.
machloket tannaim. This, that’s a מחלוקת machloket of מקדש במלוה mekadesh bemilveh
was not Rav’s case. It’s this very special case where I gave
her ninety-five and I owed her the other five, and one says
well that works because she believes she’ll get the other five, so
she says she’s okay with it. So essentially she accepted, you know,
agreed to accept it and she did get a שוה פרוטה. shaveh
prutah. Like it’s a little bit interesting. At the end of the
day, did I marry her with a hundred dollars, did I marry
her with ninety-five, but she was okay with me owing her five?
It sounds more like the latter, but according to the other one,
no, it doesn’t work. She says yes, but she doesn’t really feel
and believe yes. She really feels like she didn’t get her hundred
dollars, she’s not, doesn’t trust she’s gonna get it, so there’s not
sufficient גמירות דעת. gmar dat.
But she keeps the ninety-five though.
I understand, but you said you were gonna marry her with a
hundred, so there’s a sense like she doesn’t feel like she was
given what she was promised. In one case, she treats it like
she was given what she was promised, in the other case not.
Again, I don’t exactly get the mechanics because bottom line, right, are
you marrying her with ninety-five, are you marrying her with a hundred?
If you’re marrying her with a hundred, you didn’t give her the
hundred. If you’re marrying her with ninety-five, what does this כסיפא מילתא
kesifa milta matter? Okay, but presumably you’re marrying her with ninety-five as
long as she feels she got what she was promised. Okay, so,
but that’s, so that’s the debate. And now we understand why it
works by קרקע. karka. Because by קרקע, karka, it’s not about a
husband and wife, it’s about a business deal. So of course the
guy’s gonna demand the other five thousand dollars. You know, we agreed
hundred, we didn’t say ninety-five. There’s no question he feels he’s gonna
get it and he’s gonna sue me in court if he doesn’t
get it. So there it works. But between me and my wife,
she might feel that she’s being forced to be מוחל mochel and
she’s not happy with it and therefore it might not work. So
it’s a very special case. Okay, but it’s, even though it says
מקדש במלוה, mekadesh bemilveh, it is not Rav’s classic מקדש במלוה. mekadesh
bemilveh. It’s a very special case. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this. ואלא הא דאמר רב אלעזר, Ve-ella ha de’amar Rav Elazar, התקדשי
לי במנה, hitkadshi li be-maneh, but one minute, how does this sit
with what Rav Elazar says? Because Rav Elazar says if a man
says to a woman, marry me with a hundred
dollars, התקדשי לי במנה, hitkadshi li be-maneh, ונתן לה דינר, venatan lah
dinar, and here’s five dollars, down
payment. Okay. הרי זו מקודשת וישלים. Harei zu mekudeshet veyashlim. It works
and just finish paying the other ninety-five. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לימא כתנאי אמרה לשמעתיה? Leima kitnai amrah lishmateih? Is that going only
like one of the opinions? Because by this case about the ninety-five
and only five dollars left, it was a debate if it worked.
So here’s the mirror image. So it seems like it’s only follow,
like it seems like that’s only following one of those two opinions.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר לך, Amar lach, you can
say, מנה חסר דינר כסיפא לה מילתא למיתבע. maneh chaser dinar kesifa
lah milta lemitba. A hundred minus, minus you know, five, ninety-five dollars,
she’s embarrassed to ask for the other five. So therefore because she’s
embarrassed to ask, she’s been forced to say yes, but she’s not
happy with it, and it doesn’t, and it doesn’t work. Okay, but
right, מנה חסר תשעים ותשעה, maneh chaser tishim vetishah, but a hundred,
it’s giving it one, I think five, anyway, a hundred minus ninety-nine,
right, if you only got one dollar and you owe ninety-nine, לא
כסיפא לה מילתא, lo kesifa lah milta, she’s obviously gonna demand the
rest, and since she’s obviously gonna demand the rest, there is גמירות
דעת gmar dat and it does work. Okay.
That is unbelievably ridiculous in some way. No. I get it, like
the way they, but like, she’s getting so much less than what
was promised right now, upfront.
The rest is owed to her, and as long as she trusts
she’ll get what is owed to her, then there’s גמירות דעת. gmar
dat. She
didn’t get the money, is the marriage still in effect? No, that’s
what he says, וישלים, veyashlim, that presumably not, presumably then he, you
know, was all on the understand, oh, that’s a good point because
if not then the, no you know what, it seems like, it
seems like the answer would be that yes it would, because if
the answer was that it wouldn’t, then the כסיפא מילתא kesifa milta
wouldn’t matter because כסיפא מילתא… kesifa milta
yeah, it’s a good
question. I think that it should, logically it shouldn’t matter whether she
gets it or not.
Yeah. But wait, wait, wait, wait. You’re gonna sell me your condo.
Okay. Yeah. For a hundred thousand dollars. So I’m gonna give you
ninety-five thousand dollars. You’re gonna be apt to, you’ll be inclined to
trust me for the remainder. Right. I’m gonna give you a hundred
dollars. I’m good for the rest, don’t worry.
Happens, happens every day. You ever hear of a mortgage? This happens
every single day. Exactly that.
No, it’s not because the bank puts the money on the table.
You got your money. You sold the condo. You get the money.
You didn’t get it from me.
Oh, that’s true. Oh, that’s true. Oh, that’s true. Anyway, what can
I tell you? Okay, I’m sorry. Anyway, but David asks a good
question, you know, which is, is the קידושין kiddushin dependent on paying
the remainder of the loan? It sounds like here not. It sounds
like here that otherwise we wouldn’t have a debate, and we’ll just
say let’s wait to see if the rest of the money gets
paid. You know, it sounds like it definitely works right now, but
the rest is owed. Okay, but is the fact that it’s owed,
does that, the fact that she’s being owed the rest create a
lack of her גמירות דעת? gmar dat? That’s what I was saying
before, is he marrying... Is he marrying her with the hundred or
marrying her with the ninety-five? It sounds like he's marrying her with
what he gave her, the rest is a debt. But does the
fact that the rest was left as a debt undermine her גמירות
דעת? gemar das? And if she's not certain she's going to get
it, then we say it does undermine her גמירות דעת. gemar das.
Okay, so that's anyway, that's dealing with that, although that did seem
to straight up be a debate of תנאי tannai around רב, Rav,
we gave it we made we said that it was a special
case. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, back to רב's
Rav's basic position of מקדש במלוה. mekadesh b'milveh. So it says like
this, where is it? מיתיבי, Meseivei, האומר לאשה התקדשי לי בפקדון שיש
לי בידך. ha'omer l'isha hiskadshi li b'pikadon she'yesh li b'yadeich. You know,
you know honey, you're holding on to my whatever it is, to
my no, to my let's say we'll have to have things that
have a lot of them, you know, to my bag of grain,
just keep it. And as for כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay, בפקדון
שיש לך בידך b'pikadon she'yesh lach b'yadeich והלכה ומצאתו v'halcha u'metzaso she
said yes, and it was in her house, and then she went
to to get she went to the room that it was being
stored in, שנגנב או שאבד, shenignav o she'avad, and she saw that
it had been stolen or lost, אם נשתייר ממנו שוה פרוטה, im
nishtayer mimenu shaveh prutah, if there's a little bit of grain left,
a שוה פרוטה's shaveh prutah's worth of grain, מקודשת, mekudeshes, it works
because, as long as which is interesting, why don't you say that
there wasn't גמירות דעת, gemar das, she thought she was going to
get to keep the whole thing? But anyway, let's bracket that for
now, I gave her what I gave her that, as long as
the thing had a שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah left to it, then
that was כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin and it works.
ואם לאו אינה מקודשת.
v'im lav einah mekudeshes.
Is she like שומר חנם shomer chinam or שומר שכר? shomer sachar?
She put in אבידה?
aveida? Presumably not. Okay, because I'm not being I'm not giving her
back the money she might owe me, even if she doesn't owe
me any money, I'm just giving her the money that's left, right?
I mean the גמרא's Gemara's going to get to that in a
minute, okay, but hold on, now we're assuming she doesn't owe me
any money, but as long as there's something left for her to
take for her to own, it works. ובמלוה, u'v'milveh, but if I
say marry me with a
loan, אף על פי שלא נשתייר ממנו שוה פרוטה מקודשת, af al
pi she'lo nishtayer mimenu shaveh prutah mekudeshes, then even if there's none
of the I gave her a hundred dollars and I said marry
me with that hundred dollars that I lent you, and then she
goes back and I don't know, it got stolen out of her
wallet, it doesn't matter, she's מקודשת mekudeshes because I wasn't actually marrying
her with the actual physical bill, I was marrying her with the
money she owed me, and that money I essentially gave her, I
gave her back the money she owed me, I let her keep
the money she owed me. Okay, so this is the exact opposite
of רב. Rav. This is מקדש במלוה מקודשת mekadesh b'milveh mekudeshes
even in more of a way than if it's something because here
דווקא davka I'm giving her the thing that the abstract thing and
therefore it works even if it's not around. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר משום רבי מאיר מלוה הרי הוא כפקדון. Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer mishum Rebbi Meir milveh harei hu k'pikadon. No, a מלוה milveh
is like a פקדון. pikadon. There has to be some of that
money left in order for her to be married. So anyway, you
hear both positions here are against, right? You know, at most, excuse
me, whoa.
You
know, both positions here are against רב. Rav. One says even if
none of the money is around, and the other says oh, if
some of the money is around for the מלוה milveh that can
work. But רב Rav said even if all of the money is
around for a מלוה, milveh, it doesn't work because it's no longer
mine. Okay, עד כאן לא פליגי אלא דמר סבר מלוה אף על
גב דלא נשתייר ממנה שוה פרוטה. ad kan lo pligi ela d'mar
savar milveh af al gav d'lo nishtayer mimena shaveh prutah. I mean
the whole debate here is for the מלוה milveh to work, does
there have to be some of the original money
left? ומר סבר נשתייר ממנה שוה פרוטה אין אי לא לא. u'mar
savar nishtayer mimena shaveh prutah in i lo lo. No, only if
some of the original money is left. אי לא לא. i lo
lo. נשתייר ממנה שוה פרוטה ואם לאו לא, nishtayer mimena shaveh prutah
v'im lav lo, it doesn't work. אבל דכולי עלמא, aval d'chulei alma,
everybody agrees, מקדש במלוה מקודשת, mekadesh b'milveh mekudeshes, that it works, okay?
And that just and that it and that it's either completely giving
her the abstract money or giving her some of the physical money
even after it's already in her hands. And רב Rav says even
if the whole amount is in her hands, it still doesn't work.
So the גמרא Gemara says a real problem according to
רב. Rav. So אמר רבא דתסברא המתרצתא היא? amar Rava d'tisbra hametaretzta
hi? Wait, does that make sense? You think this ברייתא braisa actually
the text of this ברייתא braisa is good? המשבשתא היא. hamishabeshta hi.
The text of the ברייתא braisa is corrupt. Why is the text
of the ברייתא braisa corrupt? Because it's going to ask the question
Michael just asked. פקדון היכי דמי? pikadon heichi dami? The case about
the bag of grain, what's the scenario? אי דקבילה עליה אחריות, ei
d'kabila aleih achrayus,
if she is liable, like he's a שומר שכר shomer sachar liable
for the loss, so it was stolen or lost and she owes
me the money, so then it's a מלוה, milveh, she owes me
money. So essentially I'm letting her keep the money she owes me.
So then it should work even if nothing is left, if the
ברייתא braisa assumes that מקדש במלוה mekadesh b'milveh works. היינו מלוה. hainu
milveh. So then it's a מלוה milveh because then if it's all
lost, she owes me the money, I let her keep the money,
so if מקדש במלוה mekadesh b'milveh works, it should then מקדש בפקדון
mekadesh b'pikadon should work even if nothing is left. All right, אי
דלא קבלה עליה אחריות, ei d'lo kabla aleih achrayus,
how about a more simple case? She doesn't have any debt to
me. She's a שומר חנם, shomer chinam, she's not liable, and therefore
I can't marry her with the stuff that doesn't exist, it doesn't
exist. I can only marry her with the stuff that's left. That
would work. So what's the problem with that? אי דלא קבלה עליה
אחריות אי הכי אדתני סיפא, ei d'lo kabla aleih achrayus ei hachi
ad'tani seifa, why did we run to the end to contrast it
to a case of מלוה? milveh? ובמלוה אף על פי שלא נשתייר
ממנו שוה פרוטה מקודשת. u'v'milveh af al pi she'lo nishtayer mimenu shaveh
prutah mekudeshes. We say oh, but by a מלוה milveh you don't
have to have any of the money
left. נפלוג וניתני בדידיה? niflog v'nitni b'dideih? Why not make a distinction
When by a פקדון pikadon does she have to have some of
the פקדון pikadon left, some of the grain still has to be
around? שלא קיבלה עליה אחריות, shelo kiblah aleha achrayus, that she has
no liability and therefore the only thing I can marry her with
is the remainder grain. אבל קיבלה עליה אחריות, aval kiblah aleha achrayus,
but if she accepted liability, אף על פי שלא נשתייר הימנה שווה
פרוטה מקודשת, af al pi shelo nishtayer heimena shaveh prutah mekudeshes,
it'll work even if there's nothing left, because she owes me the
money and she'll be able to keep the money she owes me.
So that proves that the ברייתא braisa is corrupt. It's not the
world's greatest proof because the ברייתא braisa could have gone, could have
made a distinction within the case of פקדון pikadon and runs to,
rather runs to contrast it to a case of מלווה milveh shows
that everything in the ברייתא braisa is accurate, everything makes sense, okay
there's no logical problem but because it should have made a distinction
within פקדון pikadon and didn't, proves that there's obviously a problem in
the ברייתא. braisa. Okay so this is what he's saying in order
to get out of the challenge that the ברייתא braisa presents to
רב's Rav position.
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, chisorei michasra v'hachi katni, right? Right. They're definitely
answers.
He says, it says, so he's undermining the
authority of this ברייתא?
braisa? Right, totally. That's totally what's going on. You're right. A classic
response would have been חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chisorei michasra v'hachi katni.
במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim שלא קיבלה עליה אחריות. shelo kiblah
aleha achrayus. אבל קיבלה עליה אחריות aval kiblah aleha achrayus נעשה כמלווה
na'aseh k'milveh and in the case of a מלווה milveh here's the
הלכה. halacha. Right. The language is...
Totally. Anyway, all right but we're trying to undermine its authority. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא תני הכי, ela tani hachi, here's how
you have to read the ברייתא. braisa. We'll change it a little
bit. Okay? ובמלווה אף על פי שנשתייר הימנה שווה פרוטה אינה מקודשת.
u'vemilveh af al pi she'nishtayer heimena shaveh prutah einah mekudeshes.
So as opposed to our version, which is by מלווה milveh even
if nothing is left she is מקודשת, mekudeshes, we say, we switch
it to even if something is left, she's אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshes.
We do the exact reverse. Okay? And by a מלווה milveh even
if something is left אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshes. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר משום רבי מאיר מלווה הרי הוא כפקדון. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer mishum Rabbi Meir milveh harei hu k'pikadon. No, by a מלווה
milveh it's as good as a פקדון, pikadon, that as long as
something is left it will work. So we still have to deal
with that position that says if something is left it will work,
but the main position, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma position is that
even if that even if something is left it won't work, which
is רב's Rav position. המקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת. hamikadesh b'milveh einah mekudeshes.
Okay but now we have to explain to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי, be'mai kamifligi, so what at
okay but you have to at least explain רבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. He says that you can marry her with
the מלווה milveh if some of the original money is there. אמר
רבא Amar Rava אשכחתינהו לרבנן דבי רב, ashachtinehu l'rabbanan d'vei Rav, I
found the Rabbis there in the ישיבה, yeshiva, דיתבי וקאמרי d'yasvi v'ka'amrei
and they were sitting and explaining the following way of what this
debate is about. במלווה ברשות בעלים לחזרה והוא הדין לאונסין קמיפלגי. b'milveh
birshus be'alim l'chazarah v'hu hadin l'onnasin kamifligi.
The question is, the way רש"י Rashi understands this is, at what
stage does, remember when I gave Michael the twenty bucks? At what
stage is it considered like it became, it transferred into a loan?
Okay? Is it as soon as that twenty dollars was put in
his hand? Or does he actually have to start using the twenty
dollars? Or maybe even like plan on using the twenty dollars or
something like that? Okay, why? It logically it should be. But we're
trying to say that maybe here's the issue. When does רב Rav
say המקדש במלווה hamikadesh b'milveh doesn't work? Or when is it everybody
agrees המקדש במלווה hamikadesh b'milveh doesn't work? Is when the person I
gave the money to began using and spending the money. Then it
everybody agrees at that stage it's considered a loan and even the
remaining money that he has of it is completely his, no I
don't have any it's not mine anymore. But before he began spending
the money,
still
in his hand, still in his pocket. Can I say wait, wait,
wait, I changed my mind, give me my twenty dollars back? Okay,
so that's חזרה, chazarah, can I still retract the loan before he's
begun spending it? And let's say another case, I gave him the
twenty dollars and a wind came and blew it out of his
hands. Okay? Can Michael say oh, you know what, I that I
never took that twenty dollars, I don't owe you anything, or could
I say no, you already I already lent you the money, you
have to pay me now for it back for it. So that's
the case of אונסין, onnasin, okay? At what stage does it become
a loan and stop being my money? As soon as it goes
into his hands, or only as soon as he spends it? So
that's what we're going to say the debate
is.
So why would you say otherwise, again, then then you me taking
the?
Because since it is physically my twenty-dollar bill, maybe it only gets
abstracted as a loan once it starts getting spent. And until that
stage we do look at it as the physical object is still
mine. Okay? That you're planning on using but you haven't yet used.
You know you haven't yet made it yours, right?
Where פקדון pikadon is always... It's always mine. Okay. I put food
on your plate...
I I can
give me back my food?
Actually you could. Yeah, let's say you come to my house and
I and I served you something and then we get into an
argument and I kick you out and you say fine, but I'm
taking the I'm taking the steak that you just gave me, right?
No, I give you the right to eat my food, I'm not
giving you... Okay anyway. So
what if that's the case?
What? What's... use the לשון... lashon... I always wondered why doesn't it
use the לשון lashon מלווה milveh is... is... cannot be called back
or it can be called back... use לשון lashon because... because of
this problem, this issue. It's only when you start הוצאה. hotza.
Right, its purpose is to be spent, but it might have to
begin to be spent to actually get that...
like... it makes it more... what's the word... like... it makes it
like...
irrevocable or... Right, right. Right, right.
The justification why when we were talking previously you gave Michael the
$20, right, now we're questioning that.
So now we're now we're now we're nuancing that. We might we're
saying it might depend how at what stage after he's taken that
$20. Okay, so that's exactly what we're saying. So that's the debate.
The one that says that if there's some money left, well let's
take a look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מר סבר מלווה ברשות לווה קיימה והוא הדין לאונסין mar savar
milveh bireshut loveh kaima v'hu hadin l'onassin that the that the loan
is as soon as it's given automatically becomes in the possession of
the borrower and it cannot be retracted and the borrower is fully
liable for anything that happens to it, ומר סבר מלווה ברשות בעלים
קיימה והוא הדין לאונסין u'mar savar milveh bireshut be'alim kaima v'hu hadin
l'onassin no, no, no, until it's spent or until it's excuse me
begun to be spent as way רש"י Rashi explains it, the original
money is still owned by the owner, והוא הדין לאונסין v'hu hadin
l'onassin and he can A ask for it back and B if
something happens the original owner loses out not the borrower. Now how
does that work by the way in our ברייתא? Braita? Because our
ברייתא Braita was I lent Michael $100. He did not start- or
I gave him five 20s. He did not start using it. Okay.
Then I say or I gave Michelle five 20s as a loan.
She didn't start using it. Then I said marry me with it.
She goes back to check her purse and she sees that somebody
has swiped 80 of the 100 dollars out of it. There's only
a $20 bill left. Okay, now she hasn't started spending it. Okay,
so if you say automatically it became her money then I can't
marry her with the remaining
$20 and she owes me $100 the original or 80 whatever. And
the the other opinion that said מלווה milveh is like a פקדון
pikadon means since she didn't start spending it and there's $20 left,
that $20 is still mine. Okay, A she doesn't owe me for
the 80 because that was she's not obligated in the אונסין onassin
because she hasn't started spending it and that $20 is still mine
and I can marry her with that $20. Okay, so that's what
we're doing is say everybody agrees you can't marry her once the
borrower actually takes possession of it in a way that makes it
his. The question is is that immediate or only when the person
begins spending?
Plus she had her own money in the wallet too, if some-
I
don't know, I can't deal with those cases.
Yeah, marry her for 20 and you lost 80. Right, right.
So let's just read, let's just read one more sentence to finish
this thought. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, דאמינא להו d'amina
lehu and I said back to them, לאונסין כולי עלמא לא פליגי
דברשות לווה קיימה. l'onassin kulei alma lo peligi d'bireshut loveh kaima. Okay,
no no no, we have to distinguish between the cases. It might
be as soon as the לווה loveh takes it in his hand
he's liable for any loss. Okay, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? לא גרע
משואל. lo gara mi'shoel. It's no different than if I lent him
an object. If I lent שואל shoel is חייב באונסין. chayav b'onassin.
מה שואל דהדרא בעינא, mah shoel d'hadra b'eina, if I lent Michael
here my my iPhone and he's giving me back the same iPhone,
nevertheless חייב אונסין, chayav onassin, he he accepts liability as soon as
he takes possession of it. מלווה לא כל שכן? milveh lo kol
shekein? Certainly the money. So even if the physical $100 is still
mine before he begins spending it, but as soon as he takes
possession of it he's accepting full liability. So they said look, I
get you. In terms of explaining this debate you're right, there's a
question when does that $100 stop being the the creditor's and to
begin to be be the the the borrower's? But everybody agrees that
even if the $100 bill or the five 20s is still owned
by the original owner, as soon as the borrower takes physical possession
of it he's liable for any loss.
Any- even more than אונס, oness, even
more than אונס, oness, even מתה מחמת מלאכה meisah machamat melacha anything.
אלא
הכא, ela hacha, the debate is מלווה ברשות בעלים לחזרה איכא בינייהו.
milveh bireshut be'alim l'chazara ika beineiyhu.
The debate is not whether you're חייב באונסין, chayav b'onassin, but if
it's still mine can I demand it back or not while it's
still there. And more relevant for the- although you would say also
if I lend you a hammer, right, there's an implicit שואל פחות
משלושים יום shoel pachot mi'shloshim yom I can't demand it back before
the time that- anyway but we'll see about that. But the rel-
bottom line is what we're saying is like this. Everybody agrees that
once the מלווה milveh becomes converted into just abstract money that is
owed, I then it's no longer mine, I can't marry the woman
with it, I can't buy a plot of land with it. At
what time does it become converted to that abstract? Okay, everybody agrees
it's before the full amount is spent. But the question is immediately
when the person takes possession of it it stops being mine and
it just becomes abstract money that's owed, that's what we've been assuming,
מלווה להוצאה ניתנה. milveh l'hotza'a nitnah. Now we introduce there's another opinion
that would say that the person would have to start spending it.
Okay, but before he started spending it those bills are still mine
and therefore A I could demand them back and B I could
marry a woman with them, okay, because those bills are still mine
before they began to be spent. But when- once the person dipped
into the loan then it just becomes something that's abstract. Even before
they dip into the loan, as soon as they take possession, are
obligated for any loss and for any full liability, but nevertheless, the
question is, when does that stop being my money and just become
an abstract debt, and that's what's being debated right here.
Okay.